It's Christmas Eve, 1968.
عشية عيد الميلاد في العام 1968،
The Apollo 8 spacecraft has successfully completed
أكملت سفينة الفضاء (أبولو 8) بنجاح
its first three orbits around the moon.
أول ثلاث دورات لها حول القمر.
Launched from Cape Canaveral three days before,
انطلقت من (كيب كانفرال) قبل ثلاثة أيام،
this is the first time
هذه هي المرة الأولى
that humans have ever traveled beyond low Earth orbit.
التي يسافر فيها إنسان خارج المدار الأرضي المنخفض.
On the vessel's fourth pass,
في الدورة الرابعة للمركبة،
the Earth slowly comes into view
ظهرت الأرض ببطء
and reveals itself above the Moon's horizon.
وأظهرت نفسها في أفق القمر.
Astronaut Bill Anders frantically asks his crewmates where their camera is,
سأل الرائد (بيل أندريس) زملاءه بتلهف عن مكان الكاميرا،
grabs the Hasselblad, points it towards the window,
أخذ الـ(هاسلبلاد) ووجهها نحو النافذة،
presses the shutter,
وضغط على غالق الكاميرا،
and takes one of the most important photographs of all time:
والتقط واحدة من أهم الصور على الإطلاق:
"Earthrise."
"شروق الأرض."
When the crew was safely home a few days later,
عندما عاد الطاقم بأمان إلى الوطن بعدها بأيام قليلة،
they were asked about the mission.
سألهم الناس عن هذه المهمة.
Anders famously replied,
رد (أندريس) رده المشهور،
"We went to the moon,
"لقد ذهبنا إلى القمر،
but we actually discovered Earth."
لكننا في الواقع اكتشفنا الأرض."
What did he and his fellow crewmates feel
بماذا شعر هو وزملاؤه
in this incredible moment?
في هذه اللحظة العظيمة؟
In a study released just this past year,
في دراسة نُشرت العام الماضي،
a team of researchers at the University of Pennsylvania
قام فريق من الباحثين في جامعة (بنسيلفانيا)
examined the testimonies of hundreds of astronauts
بفحص شهادات مئات الرواد
who had the opportunity to view the Earth from space.
الذين حظوا بفرصة مشاهدة الأرض من الفضاء.
Their analysis uncovered three common feelings:
كشفت تحليلاتهم ثلاث مشاعر مشتركة،
first, a greater appreciation for Earth's beauty;
الأول: تقدير هائل لجمال الأرض؛
second, an increased sense of connection to all other living beings;
الثاني: إحساس متزايد من الترابط مع جميع الكائنات الحية الأخرى؛
and third, an unexpected, often overwhelming sense of emotion.
الثالث: شعور غير متوقع وغامر من العاطفة.
The researchers believe that seeing the Earth from a great distance
يعتقد الباحثون أن رؤية الأرض من مسافة أبعد
provokes someone to develop new cognitive frameworks
يحث المرء على إيجاد أطر معرفية جديدة
to understand what they are seeing.
لاستيعاب ما يرونه.
They believe these astronauts were forever changed
يعتقدون أن الرواد قد تغيروا للأبد
by this new view,
بسبب هذا المنظر الجديد،
this new perspective,
وهذا المنظور الجديد،
this new visual truth.
وهذه الحقيقة المرئية الجديدة.
This feeling is commonly referred to as the "overview effect."
يشار إلى هذا الشعور عامةً باسم "التأثير الكلي."
Only 558 people have ever been to outer space.
يوجد 558 فقط ممن سافروا إلى الفضاء الخارجي
558 people had the opportunity
حظى 558 فقط بفرصة
to gaze down in awe,
رؤية هذا المنظر المهيب،
to wonder at our planet
والتعجب من هذا الكوكب
floating in an infinite sea of darkness.
عائمين فوق بحر من الظلمات.
But what if that number were bigger?
لكن ماذا لو كان هذا العدد أكبر؟
Three years ago, I set off on my own mission:
منذ ثلاث سنوات، انطلقت في مهمتي الخاصة،
to see if I could bring this feeling of overwhelming scale and beauty
لأرى إن كان يمكنني إيصال هذا الشعور من الحجم الهائل والجمال
to many more people
إلى العديد من الناس
just by using one small computer
عن طريق استخدام حاسوب صغير
in my small New York City apartment.
في شقتي الصغيرة بمدينة نيويورك.
It was then, in 2013, that I launched "Daily Overview."
بدأت في 2013 "الاستعراض اليومي."
Every day, I have used satellite imagery
أستخدم يوميًا صور من القمر الصناعي
to create one expansive overhead view of our planet.
لتكوين منظر علوي شامل لكوكبنا.
More than 1,000 of these images have been created thus far,
وجدت أكثر من 1000 صورة منها حتى الآن،
and more than 600,000 people
وأكثر من 600,000 شخص
tune in for this daily dose of perspectives.
انسجموا مع هذه الجرعة اليومية من هذه الآفاق.
I create the imagery by curating photos from the massive archive
أنشأتُ الصور عن طريق جمعها من أرشيف كبير
of a satellite company called Digital Globe.
خاص بشركة أقمار صناعية تسمى "ديجيتال جلوب."
They operate a constellation of five satellites,
قاموا بتشغيل كوكبة من خمسة أقمار صناعية،
each roughly the size of an ambulance,
تقريبًا كل منها بحجم سيارة إسعاف،
that is constantly taking pictures of the Earth
وتصوّر الأرض باستمرار
as they orbit at 28,000 kilometers per hour.
في دورانهم بسرعة 28,000 كم/ساعة.
Now, what does this mean?
ماذا يعني هذا؟
Each of these satellites is equipped with a camera
كل من هذه الأقمار مزود بكاميرا
that has a focal length of 16 meters,
يصل بعدها البؤري لـ16 مترًا،
so that's roughly 290 times greater
وهذا أوضح بمعدل 290 مرة
than a DSLR camera equipped with a standard 55 millimeter lens.
أكثر من كاميرا (دسلر) المجهزة بعدسات 55 ملم
So if were able to attach one of their satellites
لذا إذا تمكنا من إرفاق أحد أقمارهم الصناعية
to the roof of this theater in Oxford,
بسطح هذا المسرح في أوكسفورد،
we could take a picture of a football,
يمكننا التقاط صورة لكرة قدم،
clearly, on the pitch at the stadium in Amsterdam.
بوضوح على ساحة استاد في أمستردام.
That's 450 kilometers away.
وهذا يبعد مسافة 450 كم.
That's incredibly powerful technology.
تعد هذه تكنولوجيا فائقة القدرة.
And I decided at the beginning of this project
وقررت في بداية هذا المشروع
that I would use that incredible technology
أنني سأستخدم هذه التكنولوجيا الفائقة
to focus on the places
للتركيز على الأماكن
where humans have impacted the planet.
التي يتأثر بها الناس نحو الكوكب.
As a species, we dig and scrape the Earth for resources,
بصفتنا أنواع، نحفر ونكشط في الأرض بحثًا عن موارد،
we produce energy,
وننتج الطاقة،
we raise animals and cultivate crops for food,
نربي الحيوانات ونزرع المحاصيل لنحصل على الغذاء،
we build cities, we move around,
نبني المدن ونتحرك فيها،
we create waste.
ونخلّف القمامة.
And in the process of doing all of these things,
وأثناء كل هذه الأشياء،
we shape landscapes and seascapes
نكوّن المناظر الطبيعية البرية والبحرية
and cityscapes with increasing control and impunity.
ومناظر المدينة مع زيادة السيطرة والإفلات من العقاب.
So with that in mind,
لذا بوضع ذلك في الحسبان،
I would like to share a few of my overviews with you now.
أود مشاركتكم بعضََا من استعراضاتي.
Here we see cargo ships and oil tankers
هنا نرى سفن الشحن وحاويات الزيت
waiting outside the entry to the port of Singapore.
بانتظار الدخول لميناء (سنغافورة).
This facility is the second-busiest in the world by terms of total tonnage,
تحتل هذه المنشأة المركز الثاني الأكثر ازدحامًا في العالم من حيث الحمولة الشاملة،
accounting for one-fifth of the world's shipping containers
بما يعادل خُمْس حاويات الشحن في العالم
and one half of the annual supply
ونصف المؤن السنوية
of crude oil.
من الغاز الخام.
If you look closely at this overview, you'll see a lot of little specks.
إذا أمعنتم النظر في هذه العروض فسترون العديد من النقاط الصغيرة.
Those are actually cows at a feedlot
في الحقيقة هي عبارة عن أبقار في حقول التسمين
in Summerfield, Texas, in the United States.
في سمرفيلد، تكساس، الولايات المتحدة.
So once cows reach a particular weight,
لذا بمجرد أن تصل الأبقار إلى وزن معين،
roughly 300 kilograms,
تقريبًا 300 كجم،
they are moved here and placed on a specialized diet.
فإنها تُنقل هنا وتخضع لنظام غذائي مخصص.
Over the next three to four months, the cows gain an additional 180 kilograms
على مدار ثلاثة إلى أربعة أشهر، يزداد وزنها 180 كجم إضافية
before they are shipped off to slaughter.
قبل أن تُشحن لأجل ذبحها.
You're also probably wondering about this glowing pool at the top there.
قد تتساءلون أيضًا عن هذه البركة المضيئة.
That gets its color from a unique combination of manure, chemicals
تكتسب لونها من تركيبة فريدة من السماد والمواد الكيماوية
and a particular type of algae that grows in the stagnant water.
ونوع معين من الطحالب التي تنمو في الماء الراكد.
This is the Mount Whaleback iron ore mine
هذا هو منجم (ماونت ويلباك) للحديد الخام
in the Pilbara region of Western Australia,
في منطقة (بيلبارا) بشرق أستراليا،
a beautiful yet scary scar on the face of the Earth.
بقعة جميلة ومع ذلك مخيفة على سطح الأرض.
Of the world's mined iron ore,
من بين مناجم العالم للحديد الخام،
98 percent is used to make steel
يستخدم 98 بالمئة لصناعة الصلب
and is therefore a major component in the construction of buildings,
ومن ثم يعتبر مكوِّن أساسي في بناء المباني،
automobiles or appliances such as your dishwasher or refrigerator.
والسيارات والأجهزة مثل غسالات الأطباق أو الثلاجات.
This is a solar concentrator in Seville, Spain.
هذا مكثف شمسي في (إشبيلية)، أسبانيا.
So this facility contains 2,650 mirrors
تحتوي هذه المنشأة على 2,650 مرآة
which are arrayed in concentric circles around an 140-meter-tall tower
وتنظَّم في دوائر متحدة المركز حول برج طوله 140 مترًا،
at its center.
في مركزه.
At the top of the tower,
في قمة البرج،
there is a capsule of molten salt
هناك كبسولة من الملح المذاب
that gets heated by the beams of light reflected upwards
التي تُسخن بواسطة أشعة من الضوء المنعكسة لأعلى
from the mirrors below.
بفعل المرايات في الأسفل.
From there, the salt circulates to a storage tank underground,
من هذه النقطة، يوزع الملح إلى صهريج تخزين،
where it produces steam,
حيث ينتج البخار،
which spins turbines
الذي يدير التوربيدات
and generates enough electricity to power 70,000 homes
ويولد كهرباء كافية لتشغيل 70,000 منزل
and offsets 30,000 tons of carbon dioxide emissions every year.
وتقلل 30,000 طن من انبعاثات ثاني أكسيد الكربون كل عام.
This overview shows deforestation in Santa Cruz, Bolivia
يوضح العرض التصحر في (سانتا كروز)، (بوليفيا).
immediately adjacent to untouched tracts of rainforest.
ويجاور مباشرةً مناطق الغابات المطيرة
Deforestation in the country has primarily been driven
نتج التصحر في الدولة في المقام الأول
by the expansion of mechanized agriculture
بسبب التوسع في استخدام الزراعة المميكنة
and cattle ranching,
وبناء مزارع للماشية،
so as the country tries to meet the demand of its growing population
لذا بينما تحاول الدولة تلبية مطالب السكان المتزايدة
and feed them,
وإطعامهم،
the sacrificial destruction of its rainforest
ضحَّت بتدمير غاباتها المطيرة
has taken place to do so.
في سبيل تحقيق ذلك.
It is estimated that the country lost 4.5 million acres of rainforest
قدرت الإحصاءات أن الدولة خسرت 4.5 مليون فدان من الغابات المطيرة
in one decade alone
في عقد واحد فقط
from 2000 until 2010.
من عام 2000 إلى 2010.
This is the Eixample district in Barcelona, Spain.
هذه منطقة (ليشامبلا) في برشلونة، أسبانيا.
So the overview perspective can be incredibly helpful
لذا فالمنظور الكلي قد يكون مفيدًا للغاية
to help us understand how cities function
في المساعدة على فهم كيفية عمل المدن
and how we can devise smarter solutions for urban planning,
وكيف نضع حلولًا مجدية للتخطيط العمراني،
and this will become only more relevant
وسيصبح هذا مناسبًا أكثر فأكثر
as it is expected that 4.9 billion people will live in cities around the world
لأنه من المتوقع أن 4.9 مليون نسمة ستعيش في المدن حول العالم
by the year 2030.
بحلول عام 2030.
This area of Barcelona is characterized by its strict grid pattern,
تمتاز هذه المنطقة في برشلونة بنمط شبكي دقيق،
apartments with communal courtyards
والشقق ذات الأفنية العامة
and these octagonal intersections
والتقاطعات ثمانيّة الأضلاع
which allow for more sunlight, better ventilation
والتي تسمح بدخول بمزيد من أشعة الشمس والتهوية الجيدة
and additional parking at street level.
ومواقف سيارات إضافية في مستوى الشارع.
And here we see that grid pattern but under much different circumstances.
ونرى هنا النمط الشبكي لكن في ظل ظروف مختلفة تمامًا.
This is the Dadaab Refugee Camp in northern Kenya,
هذا معسكر للاجئين في (داداب)، شمال كينيا،
the largest such facility of its kind in the world.
أكبر منشأة من هذا النوع في العالم.
To cope with the influx of refugees who are fleeing Somalia,
ليسع تدفق اللاجئين الفارين من الصومال،
where there is famine and conflict,
حيث يسود الجوع والصراع،
the UN has built this area gridded out at left
أنشأت الأمم المتحدة هذه المنطقة على شكل شبكي في اليسار
called the LFO extension
تسمى منطقة امتداد (LFO)
to house more and more refugees
لإسكان مزيد من اللاجئين
who are arriving and occupying these white dots,
الذين يصلون ويشغلون هذه النقط البيضاء،
which are actually tents
وهي في الواقع عبارة عن خِيَم
which will slowly fill up the area over time.
التي ستملأ المكان ببطء على مدار الزمن.
So if you have one of these overviews,
لذا إذا رأيت واحدة من هذه الاستعراضات
you have a moment in time.
فستكوّن لحظة من الزمن.
If we have two overviews, however,
أما إذا كان لديك اثنتين منها،
we are able to tell stories about changes in time.
فنستطيع حينها رواية القصص عن التغيرات في الوقت.
I call that feature of the project "Juxtapose,"
أسمي تلك السمات الخاصة بالمشروع "التجاور،"
and we'll share a few examples of it with you now.
وسأشارككم ببعض الأمثلة منها الآن.
So the tulip fields in Netherlands bloom every year in April.
تتفتح أزهار "التوليب" بـ(هولندا) في أبريل من كل عام.
So we take an image captured in March a few weeks before
التقطنا صورة في مارس قبل ذلك بأسابيع
and contrast it to one taken a few weeks later.
وقارناها مع صورة ملتقطة بعد ذلك بأسابيع.
We're able to watch the flowers bloom in this magnificent cascade of color.
تمكنا من مراقبة الأزهار تتفتح في هذا اللون الرائع عند الشلال.
It is estimated that the Dutch produce 4.3 billion tulip bulbs every year.
قدرت الإحصاءات أن هولندا تنتج 4.3 مليون زهرة توليب كل عام.
In 2015, two dams collapsed
في عام 2015، سقط سدّان
at an iron ore mine in southeastern Brazil,
في منجم للحديد الخام في جنوب البرازيل،
causing one of the worst environmental disasters
مما تسبب في إحداث أسوء كارثة بيئية
in the history of the country.
في تاريخ الدولة.
It is estimated that 62 million cubic meters of waste
قدرت الإحصاءات أن 62 مليون مترًا مكعبًا من القمامة
were released when the dams broke,
انتشرت عند انهيار السدين،
destroying numerous villages in the process,
مما أدى إلى دمار قرى عديدة أثناء ذلك،
including Bento Rodrigues, seen here before ...
بما في ذلك (بينتو رودريجوز) التي شاهدناها،
and after the flood.
قبل الفيضان وبعده.
Ultimately, 19 people were killed in this disaster.
توفي تقريبًا 19 شخصًا جراء هذه الكارثة.
Half a million people did not have access to clean drinking water
لم يستطع نصف مليون شخص الحصول على مياه شرب نظيفة
for an extended period of time,
لمدة طويلة من الوقت،
and the waste soon entered into the Doce River,
وتسربت القمامة إلى نهر دوك
extended for 650 kilometers
ممتدة لنحو 650 كم
all the way into the sea,
في طريقها إلى البحر،
killing unknowable amounts of plant and animal life along the way.
مما أدى إلى مقتل عدد مجهول من النباتات والحيوانات
And lastly, here is a story related to the crisis in Syria,
وفي النهاية، إليكم قصة مرتبطة بالكارثة في سوريا
a conflict which has claimed the lives of hundreds of thousands of people
الصراع الذي أنهى حياة مئات الآلاف
and displaced millions.
وشرد الملايين.
So this patch of desert is seen in Mafraq, Jordan in 2011,
رأينا هذه القطعة من الصحراء في (المفرق)، بالأردن عام 2011،
the year the conflict started,
السنة التي بدأ فيها الصراع.
and when we compare it to an image captured just this year in 2017,
وعندما قارناها بصورة ملتقطة في 2017،
we see the construction of the Zaatari refugee camp.
رأينا تأسيس مخيم الزعتري للاجئين.
So just as the astronauts of Apollo 8
بمجرد أن رأى رواد سفينة (أبولو8)
watched the Earth rising above the lunar landscape for the first time,
شروق الأرض من فوق سطح القمر لأول مرة
there is no way that you could have imagined
ما كان لك أن تتخيل شكل
what the places I just showed you look like from outer space.
الأماكن التي عرضتها من الفضاء الخارجي.
And while you may enjoy the aesthetics of an image,
وبينما تستمتع بجمال الصورة،
once you learn exactly what it is you're seeing,
بمجرد أن تعلم بالضبط الذي تراه،
you may struggle with the fact that you still like it.
قد لا تنسى أنها مازالت تعجبك.
And that's the tension I want to create with my work,
وكان هذا التوتر الذي أحدثه بعملي،
because I believe it is that contemplation,
لأني أعتقد أن هذا هو التفكر
that internal dialogue
وذلك الحوار الداخلي
that will lead to greater interest in our planet
الذي سيؤدي إلى اهتمام أكبر بكوكبنا
and more awareness of what we're doing to it.
ومزيدا من الوعي تجاه ما نفعله به.
I believe that viewing the Earth from the overview perspective
أعتقد أن شكل الأرض من منظور كلي آخر
is more important now than ever before.
هو الأهم الآن أكثر من ذي قبل.
Through the incredible technology of these high-flying cameras,
من خلال التكنولوجيا الفائقة لهذه الكاميرات التي تحلق عاليًا،
we can see, monitor and expose
نستطيع أن نرى ونتحكم ونعرض
the unprecedented impact that we are having.
التأثير الفريد الذي لدينا.
And whether we are scientists
وسواء كنا علماء
or engineers or policymakers
أو مهندسين أو صناع السياسة
or investors or artists,
أو مستثمرين أو فنانين،
if we can adopt a more expansive perspective,
إذا تمكنا من تبني منظور أكثر شمولًا،
embrace the truth of what is going on
والسعي وراء حقيقة ما يجري
and contemplate the long-term health of our planet,
والتفكير في خطة صحية طويلة الأمد
we will create a better
سنضمن وجود مستقبل أفضل
and safer and smarter future
وأكثر أمانًا وذكاءً
for our one and only home.
لكوكبنا الوحيد والأوحد.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)